Guide to the Time Inc. Time Publishing and Business Records 1929-1999 MS 3009-RG 24
New-York Historical Society
Time Inc. Time Publishing and Business Records
1927-1999
New-York Historical Society
Time, inc.
MS 3009-RG 24
195.25 Linear feet in 199 record cartons including 21 reels of microfilm, 1 document case, and 3 flat boxes
The Time Publishing and Business Records contain materials from the offices and staff of the business and publishing side of the magazine's operation. The majority of materials come from the office of the business manager; departments in charge of advertisements in the magazine; an educational materials subscription program; and public affairs.
Arrangement
Organized into eight series:
Series I. Publisher Henry Luce III Files
Series II. Office of the Business Manager Files
Series III. Advertising Promotion Department Records
Series IV. Promotion and Public Affairs Department Records
Series V. Advertising Sales Department Records
Series VI. Circulation Department Records
Series VII. Production and Ad Records Department Records
Series VIII. Time Education Program Files
Historical Note
Time is the first magazine created by Time Inc. with the first issue published on March 3, 1923. Time Inc. cofounders Henry R. Luce and Briton Hadden shared the masthead as Editors until Hadden's death in 1929. At this time, John S. Martin became the first Managing Editor of Time with Luce still over him as Editor. According to the Ownership Statements in the General Administrative Files, the earliest publisher of Time was Time Inc., not an individual.
According to Time Inc., Time pioneered the news magazine, at least the modern news magazine. Time's format of short articles summarizing news events and other items of interest and importance became the standard for later news magazines. Magazine sections included national and international affairs, business, education, science, medicine, law, religion, sports, books, and the arts.
Time published several foreign-language editions, the first launched in 1941 delivered by air service to Latin America; special issues including the popular Time Person of the Year (formerly Man of the Year); and Time for Kids, a children's magazine.
For the majority of Time Inc.'s existence, the company maintained a strict separation of editorial from the publishing and business side of each magazine, colloquially called the separation of "church" (editorial) and "state" (publishing). Publishing and Business Management includes the publisher, general manager, business manager, advertising sales, marketing services, letters, circulation, and public relations. Cofounder Henry Luce structured Time Inc. this way so that the business side could not (in theory) influence the editorial content of the publications. For example, the advertising sales people could not interfere with a magazine's decision to run an article on the dangers of cigarette smoking, even though it might mean losing millions of dollars in tobacco ads.
Citations:
The Editors of Encyclopaedia Britannica. "Time," Encyclopaedia Britannica. Encyclopaedia Britannica, Inc., 2018. https://www.britannica.com/topic/Time-American-magazine.
Elson, Robert T. 1968. Time Inc.: The Intimate History of a Publishing Enterprise, 1923-1941. New York: Atheneum.
Hooper, Bill. Email to Holly Deakyne, 10 June 2016.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers with the exception of restricted materials. Restricted materials include contracts, medical records, student records, and records with personally identifiable information. Restricted materials are located in boxes R26 and R56. Materials in box R28 are restricted due to mold. Unreformatted audiovisual material and digital material in the collection is not accessible. Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Related Materials
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the Time Inc. Records. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the Time Inc. Records (MS 3009). The Henry Luce Papers (MS 3014) were acquired with the Time Inc. Records. The collection of books acquired with the records are cataloged as the Time Inc. Reference Library.
Information about the history of Time and additional records from the publishing and business offices can be found in the Time Inc. Subject Files (MS 3009-RG 1) and the Time Inc. Annex Files (MS 3009-RG 39). Records from the editorial offices are in the Time Inc. Time Editorial Records (MS 3009-RG 7).
Scope and Contents
The Time Publishing and Business Records contain records from offices and staff from the publishing and business side of the magazine, not the editorial side. This includes the publisher, the office of the business manager, departments in charge of advertisement promotion, advertising sales, advertising placement, circulation, an educational materials subscription program, and public affairs.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Time Inc. in 2015.
Advertising.; Advertising -- United States.; Corporation records.; Corporations -- History.; Corporations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Corporations -- Public relations.; Exhibition records.; International relations and culture.; International travel; Organization files.; Periodicals -- Circulation; Press clippings.; Press releases.; Public relations; Publishers and publishing -- Management; Publishers and publishing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Publishers and publishing -- United States -- History; Readership surveys -- United States; Traveling exhibitions.; Time, inc. -- Archives.; Time, inc. -- History.
- Series I. Publisher Henry Luce III Files, 1969-1972; 0.25 Linear feet in 6 folders
  Biographical Note
  Henry "Hank" Luce III was the son of Time Inc. co-founder Henry R. Luce and was on staff at Time Inc. from 1951 to 1980. From 1969 to 1972, Luce served as Time Publisher.
  Luce joined Time Inc. in 1951 as a correspondent. From 1956 to 1960 he was the head of the New Building Department, planning and overseeing the construction of the Time & Life Building at Rockefeller Center. Once the new building opened, Luce held positions in the publisher's offices of Time and Fortune before becoming Fortune Circulation Director in 1961.
  In 1964 Luce joined Time Inc. corporate management as Associate Director of Research and Development. From 1966 through 1968 he held positions as the Time-Life News Service London bureau chief and as publisher of Fortune. From 1969 to 1972, Luce served as Time Publisher. After a short sabbatical, he returned to work in July 1972 as the Vice President of Corporate Planning and remained in this position until his retirement in 1980.
  Scope and Contents
  Henry Luce III Files include memoranda regarding bonuses to ad sales staff and executives of the magazine, discussion of how to promote Time Inc. magazines, salary and headcount information for Time, and memoranda and studies exploring the launch of a new magazine for business and industry.
  Arrangement
  Organized alphabetically with arrangement imposed.
  - Ad bonuses, 1970-1971 (Offsite-box 4274, Folder 20)
  - Executive bonuses, 1972 (Offsite-box 4274, Folder 21)
  - Historical data, 1969-1971 (Offsite-box 4274, Folder 22)
  - Promotion program, 1969-1970 (Offsite-box 4274, Folder 23)
  - Staff, 1969-1972 (Offsite-box 4274, Folder 24)
  - Time B, 1969-1970 (Offsite-box 4274, Folder 25)
- Series II. Office of the Business Manager Files, 1929-1977; 12.25 Linear feet in 13 record cartons
  Biographical / Historical
  The Office of the Business Manager was primarily responsible for the accounting, bookkeeping, and advertising pricing of each Time Inc. franchise. The Business Manager reported to the General Manager, when present, who reported to the Publisher.
  On the earliest paperwork retained from 1929 in the Ownership Statements files, W. W. Commons is listed as Assistant General Manager. Ownership statements from 1932 to 1940 list him as the Business Manager. In 1941 William Hoeft takes over through 1947. Eric Hodgins is listed as General Manager in 1942. In 1948 James Thomason becomes the Business Manager. Assistant Business Manager Kelso Sutton took over as Business Manager around 1962 or 1963 and remained in this role through 1968 when he moved on to become Time General Manager. According to the Department Head Lists in the Time Inc. Reference Files, John P. Keller holds the post of Business Manager for a year before Lucy Werner takes over by early 1970. She remains Business Manager through 1972 or 1973 and is no longer in the role by 1974.
  The title of Assistant Business Manager is not listed in the 1970 Department Head List. The listing returns by 1972 and includes John Howard through 1974. There are no lists from 1975 to 1977, but on the January 1978 list, Howard is the Time Business Manager. Ron Dronzek appears on the January 1978 list as an Assistant Business Manager, but by November of that year he has been promoted to Business Manager.
  Citation:
  Hooper, Bill. Email to Holly Deakyne, 11 January 2019.
  Time Inc. Reference Files, MS 3009-RG 3, New-York Historical Society.
  This series contain administrative records from Time Business Managers William Hoeft, James Thomason, Kelso Sutton, and Lucy Werner; Assistant Business Managers John Howard and Ron Dronzek; along with Time staff personnel files created by this office. The records document financial decisions for the publication of the magazine.
  The earliest records are ownership statements in the General Administrative Files. These forms were required by the Post Office to be filed annually by publishers of magazines. The statements list the publisher, editor-in-chief, managing editor, business manager, and major stockholders.
  Organized into seven series:
  Subseries II.A. Business Manager James A. Thomason Files
  Subseries II.B. Business Manager Kelso Sutton Files
  Subseries II.C. Business Manager Lucy Werner Files
  Subseries II.D. Assistant Business Manager John Howard Files
  Subseries II.E. Assistant Business Manager Ron Dronzek Files
  Subseries II.F. General Administrative Files
  Subseries II.G. Personnel Files
  - Subseries II.A. Business Manager James A. Thomason Files, 1939-1963; 1.25 Linear feet in 2 record cartons
    According to the Time Inc. staff newsletter FYI, William Hoeft had been the Time Business Manager for six years when he transferred to the Time Life International foreign desk as business manager in 1947. James Thomason took over for Hoeft at that time and served until he was promoted to Time General Manager around 1963.
    Business manager James "Gus" Thomason's files were originally in roughly chronological runs of files with some of the same titles appearing in each year similar to Sutton's files. Records include correspondence and interoffice memoranda regarding staff salaries and bonuses; advertising rates and studies; operations for advertising sales, promotion, and distribution; and Life's service charges to Time.
    Some records from Thomason for 1963 to 1964 are among folders of his successor Kelso Sutton. The similar labeling and arrangement of Thomason's and Sutton's files look like they were kept by the same third person, perhaps an administrative assistant.
    Additional files from Thomason are in the General Administrative Files.
    Organized into chronological groups of alphabetically arranged files based on the original arrangement.
    - General, 1955-1960 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 1)
    - Advertising Sales, 1939-1954 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 2-9)
    - Christmas, 1953 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 10)
    - Editorial, 1953 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 15-16)
    - Expense Accounts, 1953 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 17)
    - Stockholders Report, 1951-1953 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 18)
    - Advertising Sales, 1955, 1959 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 19)
    - Expense Accounts, 1959 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 20)
    - Advertising Sales, 1959-1961 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 21)
    - Advertising Discounts, 1961 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 22)
    - Advertising Promotion, 1960-1961 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 23)
    - Auer, Bernhard, 1961 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 24)
    - Austell, Rhett, 1961 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 25)
    - Barrows, Don, 1961 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 26)
    - Circulation, 1960-1961 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 27)
    - Comptroller's Department, 1960-1961 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 28)
    - Conflict of Interest [empty], undated (Offsite-box 770, Folder 29)
    - Distribution, 1960-1961 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 30)
    - Economic Fix, 1961 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 31)
    - Editorial, 1960-1961 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 32-33)
    - Election Issue, 1960 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 34)
    - Expense Accounts, 1960-1961 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 35)
    - Linen, James, 1960 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 36)
    - Morgue, 1960-1961 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 37)
    - Office Management and Space, 1960-1961 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 38-39)
    - Life, 1961 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 40)
    - New Staff Parties, 1956-1962 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 41-43)
    - Purchasing Practices, 1961 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 44)
    - Studies: Compensation Survey, 1961 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 45)
    - Suburban Home Guides, 1961 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 46)
    - Advertising Sales, 1962 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 47-48)
    - Auer, Bernhard, 1962 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 49)
    - Austell, Rhett, 1962 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 50)
    - Canadian Operation, 1962 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 51)
    - Capital Appropriations, 1962 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 52)
    - Circulation, 1962-1963 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 53-55)
    - Comptrollers Department, 1962 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 56)
    - Corporate, 1962 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 57)
    - Distribution, 1962 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 58)
    - Editorial Reference, 1962 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 59)
    - Leaves of Absence, 1962 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 60)
    - Makereadies, 1962 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 61)
    - News Service, 1962 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 62-63)
    - Office Management, 1962 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 64)
    - Purchasing Practices, 1962 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 65)
    - Service Departments and Company Administration Reports, 1962-1963 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 66)
    - Advertising Sales, 1963 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 67)
    - Austell, Rhett, 1963 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 68)
    - Circulation, 1963-1964 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 69-71)
    - Editorial Reference, 1963 (Offsite-box 770, Folder 72)
    - Leaves of Absence, 1963 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 1)
    - Legal, 1963 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 2)
    - News Service, 1963 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 3)
    - Staff Development Study Courses, 1963 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 4)
    - Staff Memoranda, 1963 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 5)
  - Subseries II.B. Business Manager Kelso Sutton Files, 1962-1964; 0.75 Linear feet in 1 record carton
    Kelso Sutton served as Time Assistant Business Manager from 1962 maybe through 1963. By mid-1964 he took over from James Thomason as Business Manager and remained in this role through 1968 when he moved on to become Time General Manager. Sutton held several other roles at Time Inc. eventually becoming a board member, the executive vice president of the Magazine Group then president of the Books Group.
    Business manager Kelso Sutton's files look similar to Thomason's files. Records include correspondence and interoffice memoranda regarding staff salaries and bonuses; advertising rates and studies; operations for advertising sales, promotion, and distribution; and Life's service charges to Time.
    Some records from the prior business manager James Thomason for 1963 to 1964 are in Sutton's files. The similar labeling and arrangement of Thomason's and Sutton's files look like they were kept by the same third person, perhaps an administrative assistant. Along with Thomason's, there are some folders from Assistant or Associate Business Manager Rose Epstein with the same label format. It appears that her files, as an assistant, were integrated into Sutton's and Thomason's as the head of the office.
    Organized alphabetically.
    - Administration, 1963-1964 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 6)
    - Advertising Promotion, 1963-1964 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 7)
    - Advertising Sales, 1964 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 8)
    - Budget, 1964 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 9)
    - Cable Distribution Service, 1964 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 10)
    - Circulation, 1963-1964 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 11-14)
    - Cleveland Council on World Affairs, 1964 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 15)
    - Copy Transportation, 1962-1963 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 16)
    - Editorial Reference, 1964 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 17)
    - Expense Accounts, 1964 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 18)
    - Fortune 500 by Time Regions, 1964 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 19)
    - Hilton Hotel Reservations, 1964 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 20)
    - Hydrofoil, 1964 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 21)
    - International Marketing Institute, 1964 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 22)
    - Jamaica Convention, 1964 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 23)
    - Leaves of Absence, 1964 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 24)
    - Legal, 1964 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 25)
    - Luce-Donovan Dinner, 1964 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 26)
    - Marketing Services, 1964 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 27)
    - News Service, 1964 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 28)
    - Portraiture Exhibition, 1964 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 29)
    - Staff Memoranda, 1964 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 30)
    - Sterling Forest [empty], undated (Offsite-box 771, Folder 31)
    - Subscription Service, 1962-1964 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 32-35)
    - Time Fourth of July Issue, 1964 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 36)
  - Subseries II.C. Business Manager Lucy Werner Files, 1970-1972; 0.25 Linear feet in 5 folders
    In 1969 the Department Head List shows Lucy Werner in the Comptroller's office as an accounting assistant. By early 1970, she is the Time Business Manager, a role she holds through 1972 or maybe 1973. By 1974, she is in Corporate Administration as the head of union relations.
    Lucy Werner's files seem to focus mainly on international offices and publication of Time primarily in Canada and Australia. Records include correspondence and interoffice memoranda with the international offices and expense and profit projections.
    - Canadian Business Manager, 1971-1972 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 37)
    - Foreign Syndication, 1972 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 38)
    - South Pacific, 1970-1971 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 39)
    - Time Canada, 1970-1971 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 40)
    - Time-Life International (Australia) Pty Ltd, 1971 (Offsite-box 771, Folder 41)
  - Subseries II.D. Assistant Business Manager John Howard Files, 1970-1977; 3 Linear feet in 4 record cartons
    John Howard's files document financial decisions for the publication of Time edition distributed in Canada. The records include papers from the managing director of Time Canada Stephen LaRue.
    Records discuss business operations, Canadian staff, and the proposal to close Time Canada due not being able to comply with content regulation requirements in Canadian bill C-58. Records include financial statements, a submission to the special senate committee on mass media, a presentation created for parlimentary hearings on bill C-58, and correspondence with the Canadian business office.
    Time Canada Ltd. / Time Canada Files are organized chronologically due to timeline of events up through possible closure. One file not related to Canada is at the end.
    - Time Canada Ltd. / Time Canada Files, 1970-1973 (Offsite-box 3136, Folder 10-21)
    - Time Canada Ltd. / Time Canada Files, 1973-1975 (Offsite-box 3137)
    - Time Canada Ltd. / Time Canada Files, 1975-1976 (Offsite-box 3138)
    - Time Canada Ltd. / Time Canada Files, 1976-1977 (Offsite-box 3139, Folder 1-13)
    - Time Canada Ltd. / Time Canada Files [RESTRICTED], 1960-1975 (Offsite-box R26, Folder 45-51)
    - International Editorial: Greens, 1975-1976 (Offsite-box 3139, Folder 14)
  - Subseries II.E. Assistant Business Manager Ron Dronzek Files, 1974-1977; 0.5 Linear feet in 9 folders
    Ron Dronzek's files document financial decisions for publication of the Time international edition distributed in Australia. The records include some papers from the managing director of Time South Pacific Edward Barnum.
    Records include advertising statistics, a subscriber survey, staff salary reviews, newsstand sales reports, and profit and loss projections.
    Organized chronologically.
    - Time South Pacific Files, 1974-1977 (Offsite-box 3136, Folder 1-9)
  - Subseries II.F. General Administrative Files, 1929-1975; 191570; 4.5 Linear feet in 5 record cartons
    Office of the Business Manager General Files contain administrative files spanning the tenure of several business managers, primarily William Hoeft and James A. Thomason. The files were originally found together and not separated by office holder. Records document financial decisions for the publication of Time and include ownership reports, meeting minutes of the business manager meetings, profit studies, circulation studies, production costs, and Time Inc. policies.
    - General, 1937-1955 (Offsite-box 779, Folder 1-3)
      Include records on circulation history, target figures, staff targets, office space requirements, georgraphic cost comparisons, metallic ink prices, expenses of various departments at Time, March of Time program costs, and lists of advertisers.
    - ABC: Publisher Statements, 1957; 191571 (Offsite-box 779, Folder 4)
    - Advertising, 1937-1953; 191576 (Offsite-box 779, Folder 5-7)
    - Advertising Promotion, 1946, 1956-1957; 191572 (Offsite-box 779, Folder 8-9)
    - Advertising Sales, 1938-1957; 191574 (Offsite-box 779, Folder 10-13)
    - Advertising Studies, 1942-1945; 191577 (Offsite-box 779, Folder 14-15)
    - Age Data: Executives, 1952; 191582 (Offsite-box 779, Folder 16)
    - Atlantic City Meeting, 1956; 191583 (Offsite-box 779, Folder 17-18)
    - Breakeven Points, 1938, 1945-1949; 191584 (Offsite-box 779, Folder 19-21)
    - Budgets, 1950-1956 (Offsite-box 3139, Folder 15-20)
    - Business Manager's Meetings, 1949-1950; 191586 (Offsite-box 779, Folder 22)
    - Capital Appropriations, 1957; 191587 (Offsite-box 779, Folder 23)
    - Christmas, 1957; 191588 (Offsite-box 779, Folder 24)
    - Circulation, 1943-1951; 191589 (Offsite-box 779, Folder 25-26)
    - Circulation, 1956-1957 (Offsite-box 3131, Folder 1-2)
    - Circulation Study, 1965; 193192 (Offsite-box 3131, Folder 3)
    - Communications, 1957; 191590 (Offsite-box 3131, Folder 4)
    - Comparative Studies, 1945-1952; 191591 (Offsite-box 3131, Folder 5-6)
    - Comptroller Department, 1955-1957; 191592 (Offsite-box 3131, Folder 7)
    - Conference: "The Environment of Change", 1964; 193193 (Offsite-box 3131, Folder 8)
    - Cost Control Bulletins, 1949; 191593 (Offsite-box 3131, Folder 9)
    - Cresap, McCormick and Paget, 1957; 191594 (Offsite-box 3131, Folder 10)
    - Distribution, 1952-1957; 191596 (Offsite-box 3131, Folder 11-13)
    - Economics Relative to Price Control, 1946; 191599 (Offsite-box 3131, Folder 14)
    - Editorial, 1941-1958; 191600 (Offsite-box 3131, Folder 15-19)
    - Editorial: Art Book, 1957-1958; 191601 (Offsite-box 3131, Folder 20)
    - Editorial: Color, 1946 (Offsite-box 3131, Folder 21)
    - Editorial: Operations, 1957 (Offsite-box 3131, Folder 22)
    - Foreign Desk, 1952; 191602 (Offsite-box 3131, Folder 23)
    - 40th Anniversary Dinner, 1963; 191603 (Offsite-box 3131, Folder 24)
    - Guild, 1957-1958; 191604 (Offsite-box 3131, Folder 25-26)
    - Larson, Roy E., 1957; 191605 (Offsite-box 3131, Folder 27)
    - Life, 1957; 191606 (Offsite-box 3131, Folder 28)
    - Linen, James A., 1953-1957; 191608 (Offsite-box 3131, Folder 29-30)
    - Makereadies, 1957; 191609 (Offsite-box 3131, Folder 31)